Heat. Heat.
>> [music]
[cheering]
>> The 1930s saw Germany turn from a
shattered nation into a military
powerhouse. It was to wage war on the
nations which just 11 years earlier had
[music] left Germany a broken country
and a population bereft of pride in the
wake of [music] World War I.
[cheering]
>> One man created this transformation,
Adolf Hitler.
>> Hitler was one of the few people in
Germany who welcomed another war. He
wasn't scared.
Hitler's magnetism was not only
something which could convince enormous
crowds but was also incredibly powerful
[music] like a potent narcotic.
>> How did he become the most powerful man
in Germany? Who were the Nazis and how
did they reinvigorate this fractured
nation?
In VHimar, Germany, there was a new kind
of energy, very visible on the streets.
They wanted perpetual acclamation. They
wanted constant support from the people.
>> Terror played a very important part in
media leadership. Nothing would be
tolerated that undermined the German
national revolution. [cheering]
>> Thousands were taken in by one man's
[music] magnetism, which proved to be
Germany's fatal attraction.
Hitler at this stage uh sees himself not
as the Messiah but as the John the
Baptist. It's only at his time in
Lansburg prison that he actually
realizes my God I am he.
[screaming]
To fully understand the doomed love
affair of Germany and Hitler, we must
first look into the German nation of the
late 19th century.
>> Germany had become the most powerful
country, the most prosperous country,
[music] the most advanced country on the
European continent. It was a rather
authoritarian state on the one hand,
[music] but it also had a national
parliament with elections [music] with
some limited powers, but those powers
are most likely growing.
>> A highly militarized imperial state
under the hereditary monarchy of the
Horn Zullern dynasty.
Having given support to the unification
of Germany after the Franco-Russian War,
Britain had become fearful of this new
power. Its growing industrial and
military capability threatened to
overshadow Britain's diminishing empire.
>> After the Francoressussian War, Germany
powered ahead economically,
uh, overtaking Britain as an industrial
power by the time of the First World
War, second only to the United [music]
States. There was a great deal of
catching up to do a great deal of nation
building, of creating unity, of creating
vision. It
>> was ambitious really to join the other
great powers as one of the major
European [music] imperial states.
>> Alongside that, both envy and arrogance
of the British Empire. It was envy
[music] because it was so world
powerful. It was 25% of the world's
surface and 25% [music] of the world's
people. But in in addition, very strong
sense of superiority.
Many historians would say a dangerously
expansionist power with ambitions in
Europe that were certainly threatening
to the continuation of any existing
balance of power.
>> It was a mass of sething tensions.
>> Germany was beginning to be a colonial
power late in the race.
It is not in Germany, however, where our
story begins, but in neighboring
Austria, Hungary.
>> We don't know much about Hitler's early
life. He was born in Brown on the river
Inn on the 20th of April 1889. The son
of a minor Austrian official.
>> His father wasn't a very nice man.
Knocked Hitler around a bit. Because of
that, Hitler's mother took on a very
protective role. We can gather that
much.
>> He had a rather unhappy childhood. He
had four siblings who died before uh
before he was born.
>> Hitler's childhood leads us to believe
it was a fairly ordinary upbringing
comparable with his peers at the time.
>> A problem for historians is that Hitler
reinvented quite a bit about his
childhood. [music]
>> He was um an indifferent student. It has
to be said. It was not that he was not
uh very intelligent. He certainly was,
but he was unable to focus.
>> Bit of a learner as he continued to be,
but always a various reader. He read
everything he could get his hands on.
[music] Continued to do that.
>> He created in a sense a kind of
self-education which was a bizarre
bricklage of all kinds of sources of his
own authorship. In other words, what he
didn't get was really a coherent
education because he [music] didn't pay
attention.
>> In 1907, a young Adolf Hitler made his
way to Vienna to pursue a career as an
artist. Vienna at the time was the city
leading Europe in new artistic practice
and [music] philosophical thought.
Hitler's plan was to apply and enroll at
the Academy of Fine Arts. He went to
Vienna when he was about 16 and really
knocked around. Didn't do a lot. He
never lived as rough as he later
claimed.
>> He was rejected from art school. Um I
think probably rightly looking at his at
his artworks. Uh he knew about art in
general terms. He knew about
neocclassical art. He knew the power of
art above all that great historic images
had enormous moments. So although his
watercolors didn't advance the Nazi
cause, he knew what art could do.
>> Hitler uh claimed uh throughout his life
that he was an artist who was torn from
his easel by the love of Germany.
>> His mother was generous to him. She
provided him with a series of allowances
possibly without the knowledge of his
father. So some biographers of Hitler
say that he he was really a bit of a
layabout. He frequented cafe society in
Vienna and met up with a a deeply flawed
cafe intelligencia who fed him a lot of
the ideas that Hitler later said in mine
camp became the granite foundations of
my thought. Everyone assumes that Hitler
was strongly influenced by Austrian
anti-semitism. There was a lot of it
around before 1914. [music]
But actually, it's very hard to pin down
that he was influenced by it. All of the
associations with Jewish people [music]
with whom there are a great many in
Hitler's early life were not merely
positive but benevolent. The doctor who
treated his mother when she was sick,
the family doctor who treated all of
them, he was Jewish. The uh dealer who
uh bought and sold the paintings Hitler
painted in in Vienna to keep the roof on
the door again was Jewish.
In receipt of the inheritance bequeathed
to Hitler from his father's estate and
finding little fortune as an artist in
Vienna, Hitler decided to move to Munich
in 1913.
>> Hitler was very conscious of being
ethnically German. As a German
nationalist,
Hitler believed that he belonged more in
Germany than in Austria.
>> AustriaHungary remained a great power
[music] in the scheme of things,
dominating a large part of southeastern
[music] Europe. But I was getting into
crisis because of the growth of
nationalism, Czech nationalism,
Hungarian, South Slav. And the clash of
these national groups in the
parliamentary assemblies made the
parliament, the riceerout and its
Hungarian equivalent more or less
unworkable, ungovernable. Every meeting
just erupted into shouting matches
between the different national groups
either in Austria or in Hungary. And
that I think gave Hitler a contempt for
parliamentary rule. He saw it as being
ineffective. He saw the empire, his
large ramshackle organization. Uh and he
thought that an authoritarian director,
strong leadership, even a dictator was
the only way to solve these problems.
>> It was the assassination of Arch Duke
France Ferdinand of Austria in Sievo
that would be the catalyst for [music]
the start of the first world war. Within
weeks, Austria Hungary were at war with
Serbia. Germany then mobilized, invaded
Luxembourg and Belgium, and began to
march on France. This prompted Britain
to declare war on Germany. Hitler,
although an Austrian citizen living in
Munich at the time, managed to [music]
sign up to the German army. In the chaos
of mobilization in August 1914, his
papers were kind of disregarded and and
he got into [music] the into the army.
>> The Austrian authorities were after him.
He'd eluded conscription from the
Austrian army and was living in Germany.
He didn't want to fight for something he
didn't believe him and he certainly
didn't believe in the Hapsburgs and in
their empire.
With war erupting all over Europe,
Germany would arrive in the position of
fighting a war on two fronts. To the
east against the Russians and to the
west against Britain, France and
Belgium. Hitler had joined the army in
support of the German Empire.
The experience of war would change the
trajectory of his life and in turn the
lives of millions of others forever.
Having failed as an artist, Hitler found
himself in Munich, a city in the modern
German Empire. He signed up to the
German army and was sent to the Western
Front. Here he found Germany at war with
Britain and its allies.
>> Adolf Hitler played but an obscure part,
a corporal in the German army.
[music]
>> Hitler was fascinated by the prospect of
war.
>> The First World War turned a nobody into
a somebody. On the whole, most reports
show that he was a good soldier, well
disciplined. Um, he was promoted to an
NCO rank.
>> He survived it from start to finish.
Now, of course, not everybody did.
>> He served as a a battalion runner,
close enough to the front line, though
he didn't spend as much time as a
frontline combat infantry soldier as he
later claimed, but he was in danger. He
was within firing range of British and
French artillery because at the very
least if you're a runner you had to get
messages up to communications trenches
and he was seriously gassed in 1918.
>> People have tried to belittle what he
did in the war actually but he won the
Iron Cross secondass and then the iron
cross first class
>> on the recommendation ironically of a
Jewish superior officer. this idea that
he was some kind of of coward as
rubbish. He he actually manifested uh
enormous courage.
>> But messengers were often regarded by
the fighting [music] troops as having a
rather a cushy time.
>> The enigma is why he was never promoted
an officer. Of course,
>> maybe apocryphal, but [music]
I think it's been said that he remained
a corporal because he didn't have
leadership [music] qualities.
Hitler does not seem to have been
well-liked or well respected by his
fellow soldiers. He was a bit of a loner
regardless a bit of an eccentric. He
himself looked back on the first world
war as a time of unity, fellow feeling,
brotherhood and so on and mythologized
it in his [music] own mind until he came
to want to recreate the spirit of 1914
when all Germans united behind the
Kaiser. Uh in the Third Reich in 1933,
>> Russia mobilized its military and
defeated AustriaHungary, but was stopped
in Prussia by the German forces.
Germany being the far stronger military
power forced the Boleviks to sign the
Treaty of Breast Lipovsk. The Baltic
states were given to Germany along with
the recognized independence of Ukraine.
>> Early in 1918, they had actually signed
the treaty of Brelatovs with Russia. And
so they'd acquired an empire in Russia.
>> The dreaded two-front war [music] now no
longer existed from March 1918. So that
was taken as a sign that Germany was
doing really well in the war. And it all
hung on the Western Front. But with the
United States in the war, Germany wasn't
going to win on the Western Front.
Swiftly the menace of war grew into
dread reality as American ships and
ships carrying American citizens were
torpedoed sent to the bottom by the
ruthless campaign of the unseen Tigers
at the sea.
>> America entered the war after Germany
had started attacking all commercial
ships heading for Britain which had
meant the sinking of American ships in
the North Atlantic. On April 6th, 1917,
America declared war on Germany. With
the superior resources the Americans
brought, the German army faced an
impossible situation.
On November 11th, 1918, the armistice
was [music] signed, which ended the war.
>> The problem was that the political and
military establishment had not led
Germans to expect defeat.
>> It's all near the end, and their press
are not telling them just how effective
the counterattack of the Allies has
been. propaganda was still being [music]
pumped out saying that they were going
to win. So in late October when they
finally conceded defeat and began to sue
[music] for peace, this came as a
terrible shock. It was very very sudden
to most Germans. And then on top of that
there were the armistice terms and then
even more the peace terms in 1919 which
almost all Germans regarded with
absolute outrage.
The Treaty of Versailles was a series of
provisions and conditions [music]
placed on Germany by the Allied nations.
One of these being Germany accepting the
[music] responsibility for all loss and
damage caused by the war.
This was known as article [music] 231,
which later became known as the war
guilt clause. The treaty also forced
Germany to make substantial [music]
territorial concessions and pay
reparations to the Allied countries. In
addition, Germany was only allowed a
military force of no more than 100,000
[music] men.
>> Versailles was to them the stab in the
back. What they'd uh given was an
armistice, [music] not a surrender.
>> The Germans had to surrender their
combat aircraft. They weren't allowed to
build any combat ships. Uh their army
was restricted to 100,000. 100,000
[music] seems quite a lot to me actually
that this meant all the cooks and bottle
washers and pen [music] pushers were
counted in the 100,000 men. It wasn't
100,000 fighting men. They had to
[music]
pay massive financial reparations for
the damage that German troops had caused
in the occupation of northern France and
southern Belgium. And they rested on the
wargilt clause which almost all Germans
disputed. Germany had not been guilty
for starting the first world war. would
have been caused by the encirclement of
Germany by the uh the allies.
>> They felt [music] that the allies had
deceived them, had abandoned all notions
of honor by treating them as a conquered
[music] people when they didn't think
they were. The things that had been
promised to them, specifically by
President Woodro Wilson and David Lloyd
George, had not been delivered. [music]
Instead, they'd been violated. Their
honor had been degraded. very large
[music] proportion of them felt a very
great deal of resentment against the
rest of the world.
>> Hitler was devastated by that like huge
numbers of Germans.
>> Hitler like many others couldn't explain
it. Had to find some way of explaining
it to himself. And like tens of
thousands of others, he blamed the
homeront. [music] He blamed socialist,
Marxist, Jews, people who undermined
Germany from within.
The stab in the back theory surfaced in
right-wing circles after the end of the
war as a way to explain the sudden
defeat. It was believed that the
left-wing Republican [music] and Jewish
populations of Germany who had made up
the home front had lost the war from
within.
>> Most Germans did not believe in the stab
[music] in the back legend. the
independent social democrats and the
mainstream social democrats and then the
communist party in the early 20s were a
major part of the German political uh
system about a third of the electorate.
So this belief in the stab in the back
and a Jewish conspiracy in 1918 to 19
was very much a lunatic fringe group on
the right.
The first world war had seen the young
Hitler in a role which suited him.
However, the sudden loss for Germany was
too much to take, not only for Hitler,
but for the entire population. This,
along with the humiliation of
Versailles, Hitler and a dangerous
minority of the right-wing population
looked [music] for a scapegoat.
The search would see the birth of a new
party and bring together some of the
most dangerous men Germany has ever
produced.
The shock defeat of Germany in World War
I left the nation humiliated. The
signing of the Treaty of Versailles
saddled Germany with being responsible
[music] for rebuilding the Allied
nations.
Added to this, Germany had seen its own
revolution in 1918.
However, it was not until 1919 that the
VHimar Republic was established with the
coming together of a national assembly
in Bhimar, a town in central Germany.
Germany had to pay reparations to the
victorious allies. This was really what
accelerated the great inflation. It
started [music] in 1916 when the German
government started printing money to
fund the war effort. And as we know,
printing money causes inflation.
Postwar German governments didn't make
the slightest effort to arrest
inflation. They could pin that on the
peace treaties [music] and on the
allies. It got so out of hand in 1923.
The allies stepped in. The Americans
stepped in particularly with the doors
plan.
>> The doors and young plans to schedule
Germany's reparations payments are
evolved and they failed.
>> The door's plan was the brainchild of
the American banker Charles G. Doors.
The plan was to lend [music] the German
government the money to pay back the
reparations which had not been given to
the Allied countries. America
stabilized the German currency [music]
so that the Americans could give loans
to Germany so that Germany [music] could
pay reparations to Britain, France, and
others so that Britain, France, and
others could repay loans to the United
States.
>> During this time of change and
uncertainty, Hitler was keen to continue
in the vocation which had given him
personal success. After the war ended,
he stayed in the German army, which was
vastly depleted.
>> He didn't want to leave. He liked the
army. Whatever inventions he may have
resorted to about his own service, he
felt at home within the secure
structures and hierarchies of the army.
>> He attended the [music] courses for
soldiers at at Camp Leedfeld. Uh these
uh courses were taught some of them by
the most famous academics of the era.
and wly retailed was a dart of sturdy
German ethnationalism and patriotism.
[music] They're a way of combating the
activities of the Bolsheviks.
Right-wing political propaganda
masquerading as political education.
>> Hitler proved not only a worthy pupil,
but he actually became one of them. He
[music] was recruited to actually do
this speech making this kind of
incendurary pedagoguy himself and proved
remarkably good at it. It's there that
he learns his ortorial techniques.
>> He was actually sent by the army to
which he still belonged to observe a
far-right group called the German
workers party.
>> The German Workers Party [music] was a
group founded in Munich in January 1919
by Anton Drexler, a leading member of
the occultist Tulle Society.
The party would meet regularly and
discuss ideas of nationalism. The
binding ideas of the German Workers
Party were entrenched in racism and the
hatred of Jews. It was during this
period of observation that Hitler became
more and more involved with the party's
politics. He started speaking at its
meetings and soon became clear that he
was a [music] very gifted speaker and
took on board very much these radical
anti-semitic ideas in which the war had
been lost by some conspiracy that he
imagined the Jews had been been
undertaking against Germany. Hitler,
it's been said, had a mind a bit like a
Hoover. He just sucked up and absorbed
everything he read. People like Adolf
Lance, a practicing racist and a teacher
of really bastardized Darwinism.
>> There's a whole kind of mishmash of
ideas that he puts together to form a
national socialist ideology.
Having shown his strength as a public
speaker, Hitler began to take a bigger
role in the German workers party. He
took on more responsibility soon
becoming the head of propaganda.
>> He starts not as leader that remains and
Anel Drexler but as their PR man. And
what he does is produce these amazing,
inflammatory, exciting posters and have
these mass meetings which increasingly
large numbers of people [music]
uh come to him.
>> In 1920, Hitler decided to rename the
German Workers Party in an attempt to
broaden [music] its appeal. He called it
the National Socialist German Workers
Party. A year later, after an angry
dispute which saw him threaten to leave
the party, Hitler was named president.
Now he would start to gather around him
a loyal, intelligent and brutal inner
circle.
>> In a situation of great post-war turmoil
in Bavaria and Germany as a whole,
rampant inflation, unemployment,
street disturbances, strikes, militant
political action by workers and by the
left. So Hitler was certainly looking
for a political home and he appears to
have found one.
Hitler also gathered around him bit by
bit as his reputation as a speaker of
the radical right increased a group of
acolytes, a [music] group of disciples
who uh brought their own particular
techniques and their own ideas,
personalities and reputation.
>> Hitler's closest ally at the time was
Rudolfph Hess who had been born on April
26th, [music] 1894 in Alexandria, Egypt.
like Italy, [music] he had this
extraordinary reaction at the end, you
know, that how could we have lost and so
on, who was there to blame. Uh he
drifted off into university life, but he
was a frustrated radical nationalist and
when he met Hitler, he was absolutely
transfixed by him.
>> Hess saw again international politics in
this notion of sort of struggle between
different [music] races. He was a
fanatical admirer of of Hitler. You can
see it in the the films that were taken
of him at Nuremberg rallies. His face
just glowing with naive enthusiasm.
>> The most decorated of Hitler's men was
Herman Guring from Rosenheim, Bavaria,
born January 12th, 1893.
Guring was an unusual recruit to the
infant National Socialist Party
>> at that time in the 20s. A very dashing
figure with a big military reputation.
>> He'd been quite a distinguished uh air
force pilot during the first world war.
>> He had succeeded Baron von Richtoftton
uh as head of the von Richton squadron
after the uh shooting down of the Red
Baron. So he was an amazingly glamorous
figure and [music] he maintained this
astonishing persona of the jolly ex-f
fighter pilot which the German people
found adorable. He he was not the kind
of person who [music] gravitated easily
to these radical political movements.
But Guring too had thought that Hitzer
somehow or other articulated his own
sense of resentment [music] and loss uh
and became a committed follower from
that point on.
>> One of the party's most sinister figures
was Hinrich Himmler from a Roman
Catholic middle-class family born
October 7th 1900 in Munich.
>> Himmler's father was a teacher who'd
been actually tutor to the Bavarian
royal family. Himmler had something
rather school masterly about him.
>> I think Himmler's life was really
dominated by the fact that he wanted to
fight in the first world war but [music]
was too young. You always have that
sense with him that he was frustrated in
not being able to fight on Germany's
behalf.
>> He had this very pedagogic uh kind of
scholarly dreamy manner. Of course we
know now what was going on inside him.
He was a rather eccentric patriot,
strong anti-semite and he gravitated
towards national socialism because it
seemed for him the natural home.
Martin Borman became Hitler's most
trusted disciple. The son of a post
office worker born June 17th, 1900.
>> Borman is very much the sinister
Machavellian manipulator. [music] of
course very soon joined one of the free
corps the vigilante groups that grew up
in [music] Germany in the early 1920s
was sent to prison for murdering
somebody when he emerged he again heard
Hitler and thought well you know this
[music] man articulates the things I
feel the resentment I feel the loss um
in 1918 that all shared uh and he too
became a devoted FOLLOWER
FINALLY, arguably the most intelligent
of Hitler's men, Joseph Gerbles from the
Rur Valley, born October 29th, 1897.
Gerbles was something of an oddball in
the National Socialist Movement. [music]
He had a university education. He got a
doctorate. He studied German literature
in the 19th century. He's also a
romantic nationalist and writes a novel
before even knowing Hitler [music]
called Michael which is absolutely a
description of a Hitler type figure.
[music] This idea that Hitler had of a
Germany where all Germans were united on
an equal basis had a very powerful
appeal to Gerbles [music]
>> and he was looking for a political
movement that somehow represented his
personal position. He became [music] a
good recruit for national socialist
movement
>> and a supreme ability to organize
propaganda in the most ruthless possible
way.
>> The common feelings of loss, despair,
frustration and [music] anger from
losing the first world war united these
men. However, these were not uncommon
sentiments in Germany at the time.
Something else activated and fueled
their extremism. all had experienced
some kind of revelation whilst listening
to Hitler.
>> He seemed to be an outsider, somebody
almost sent to Germany to help Germany
regain its trajectory to great past
status, to help Germany revenge itself
on [music] the allies.
>> He was fulfilling a kind of prefigured
uh role which had always existed in uh
German history and culture. Kaiser,
Frederick, Barbarasa, King Redbeard, the
man who would deliver Germany from her
enemies and specifically now those
enemies were gathering thick and furious
around them.
For Hitler, all the signs were pointing
towards a burgeoning National Socialist
Political Party. He had managed to
gather around him a loyal following and
some meetings [music] were running into
the thousands.
It was events in Italy, however, which
ignited Hitler's imagination. They would
have huge consequences [music] on the
fate of Hitler, the National Socialist
Party, and the rest of the German
nation.
Hitler had gathered some of the
brightest and most dangerous men from
the far right. His national socialist
meetings often brought in around 2,000
participants.
But Hitler's perception of himself and
his party was grossly exaggerated.
He's a kind of man in a dirty raincoat
standing on a soap box in the middle of
a town square talking to half a dozen
people
>> standing on platforms on street corners
and so on. Um you know old-fashioned
kind of political activity.
>> There were other far more powerful far
more publicly visible [music] um
right-wing parties in Germany at the
time.
>> It really was just an assembly of people
who come together who shared roughly the
same kinds of [music] views. Events in
Italy inspired Hitler.
>> The bombastic newspaper editor with a
gladiator's jaw led his black shirted
[music] legions in a march on Rome.
>> In October 1922,
the fascist leader Mussolini and his
blackshirt army marched on Rome. King
Victor Emanuel III was forced to hand
control of Italy to Mussolini. At least
this is how Hitler saw it and almost
immediately began to plot his own coup.
>> Hitler was very influenced in 1983 by
the successful um coup staged by
Mussolini.
>> Hitler conceived the idea of a march on
Berlin.
>> So he began to fantasize in 1953 that
the German state was so weak, the height
of the inflation, the crisis and so on.
He took advantage of the disintegration
of German politics in 1923 under the
press of hyperinflation, the French
occupation of the ru to seize
reparations which weren't being
delivered to [snorts] stage a coup d'eta
in uh Munich.
>> Mussolini was also well aware of the
power of propaganda.
He knew how he wished to be perceived by
the rest of Europe.
>> Hitler was one of the victims of
Mussolini's propaganda. King appointed
Mussolini head of government in a
perfectly constitutional way. It was not
a coup d'eta. It was a perfectly
constitutional act on the part of the
king if a rather weakwilled one.
>> It was all a bit of a gamble from
Hitler's point of view.
>> On November 8th, 1923, Hitler along with
600 stormtroopers [music]
surrounded the Burger Brow Keller, a
large beer hall in Munich.
Here, the state commissioner of Bavaria,
Gustaf Fonar, was holding a meeting of
around 3,000 people. Hitler marched in,
fired a shot into the air, and announced
that the revolution [music] had broken
out, and no one could leave. Overnight,
Hitler attempted to take power from
[music] Fona, but failed.
It was decided early in the morning of
November 9th that they would march out
of the beer hall towards the Bavarian
Ministry of Defense. On the way, they
were confronted by the Bavarian police.
>> Hitler hoped that the new German army,
the postimperial creation of the Reich
would support them.
>> It wasn't backed by the army. The
industrial elites refused to support it.
The civil service regarded it with
[music] contempt.
>> When the Munich police opened fire, most
of them turned tail. Some of them were
hit, some wounded, a few killed. but it
was built up into an iconic episode in
the history of the movement.
>> Hitler was arrested, put on trial.
>> His trial began on February 26th,
[music]
1924 and ended on the 1st of April.
Other conspirators [music] such as
Rudolfph Hess were also arrested and
tried in court. The whole episode seemed
to be a complete failure on the part of
Hitler and the [music] National
Socialist Party. What the behold push
does which is marvelous for the Nazis is
provide them with martrs and provide
them with a myth, a [music] legend and a
whole new symbol structure. For example,
the blood flag which is the [music] flag
carried on that very day uh and when
they fall is after that time [music]
the core sacramental edifice of the Nazi
process. said that at Nuremberg all of
the standards of the stormtroopers are
touched by the blood flag. Uh the
martyrs [music] are symbolically reeried
in vast marble sarcophagi in the center
of Munich after the Nazis uh take power
and every um year there is the famous
reenactment of the push where they march
down the streets. There is a death watch
held throughout Germany the night before
there are radio linkups.
>> [music]
>> Everything is broadcast. Great films,
smoldering beers, flames, the whole
work. And if it [music] uh sounds uh
quasi religious, it is.
>> The Nazi flag, the swastika, which
Hitler purported to have designed
[music] himself, was taken from an
ancient symbol embodying early Aryan
history.
>> The swastika is an ancient Buddhist
symbol. You see it all over India and
and China. And uh it has always been
around. It was originally a symbol of
the sun, but uh it began to be acquired
by the German right in the late 19th
century [music] as one of their symbols
because they felt it stood for the idea
of being an Aryan.
>> It was Hitler's changes to the design
which marks it [music] out as the Nazi
symbol.
The story he tells is that he invited
people to submit designs and swastikas
came in and none of them he said quite
did the job. So um he said I'll do it
myself and that's what he worked on.
It's a series of simple design formula
which are applied to it. The flag is in
the colors of red, black and [music]
white which are the old imperial colors
to contrast with the red gold and uh
black of the republic. what he did very
brilliantly and I'm almost reluctant to
say this. It's fantastic piece of
graphic design. He took it, he rotated
it to give it a sense of dynamism. He
then calculated the widths of the bars
very brilliantly. He then set it in this
circle and it doesn't quite touch the
edges which gives it a kind of vibration
and dynamism and then this red outer
bit. So in all the aesthetic there's a
massive amount of red uh to stand for
the sexualist part
>> and it just goes poof and by the 1920s
it had become the authorized symbol. He
said it was going to be the Nazi symbol
and it was the Nazi symbol.
At his trial Hitler had taken sole
responsibility for the push. It is
reported that the judges found it hard
not to acquit Hitler due to their
pro-Nazi sympathies.
Finally, the sentence [music] of 5 years
of confinement was passed.
He was also banned from public speaking,
[music]
testament to the fact that his oratory
was a key factor in the rise of the
National [music] Socialist Party.
The enforced silence and confinement
gave Hitler time for introspection.
The outlet for his thoughts now came
through the pen.
the German states, the Bible of the
Nazis.
>> He didn't actually think until the push,
it doesn't seem to us that he was the
chosen one. He was the Messiah. It's
only at his time in Lansburg prison that
he actually realizes, my god, I am he
and is somehow liberated into becoming
what he does in fact become.
>> He served less than a year of his
sentence. He served with Rudolfph Hess
amongst others and he used the time to
write mine camp.
>> Democracy is a monstrosity
born of filth and fire.
>> It's interesting that Hitler decided
when he was sent off to prison in 1924
that he would take this opportunity to
sit back and write a book about his
experiences, [music] how he'd reached
the point he'd reached, why he had the
beliefs that he did. But it was very
important for him to do that. I [music]
think to to sit back and take stock of,
you know, of how he arrived there.
>> Hitler's title for the original
manuscript was my 4 and a half year
struggle against lies, paradise, and
stupidity, a final reckoning with those
who would destroy the German nation.
Well, his publishers recommended to
Amigo for something that might be a
little snappier and catchier for the
market. So they extrapolated the two
words my struggle mine camp.
>> The really interesting part of it is the
famous fifth chapter which is a theory
of propaganda. Uh the rest of it are
really a collation of emotional [music]
spasms. It's not a recipe for a system
as uh for example Marxis with the
communist manifesto as capital.
>> God has made Germans a race of supermen.
Almighty God, bless our German blood.
>> The publishers shifted 300,000 copies
and many more for perhaps obvious
reasons after after that. Big book, big
the original thing, hefty volume. You're
talking about 600 pages.
The writing of Mine Camp fueled [music]
his desire for power and the need to
lead Germany. However, Hitler knew he
would need a different route to
domination, [music]
but without being able to speak
publicly, it would have to wait.
>> Stopping him from speaking was going to
keep the peace. He was regarded as an
influential speaker.
>> I think if we're looking for an
explanation for why it took a long time
for the party to revive again and for
[music] the public to really take Hitler
seriously again, it was the ban on his
speaking.
>> He alone in Germany is not allowed to
speak. So used that as propaganda really
to attack the VHimar government for
censorship.
>> In 1927 the ban on Hitler's public
speaking was relaxed and later lifted
completely once more. Hitler took to the
stage.
>> Something about his performances.
Something about that which really
attracted people you know like modern
day pop [music] stars. There were people
who do appear to have been mesmerized by
him.
>> As soon as he could start speaking, you
have that runup to the successful
parliamentary elections in the late
1920s. When I look at Hitler on the
stage, I think of him as being in a
political theater, but I don't believe
that what he says is great oratory.
At the time of Hitler's silence, Germany
began to see a certain recovery. Thanks
to American investment, unemployment was
declining and the economy was improving.
A sense of optimism rippled through the
German nation.
A
>> lot of Americans invested, so Germany
looked as if it was prospering. By 1928,
>> the National Socialists could have been
banished to the history books as a
marginal farright political party with
their eccentric leader and the failed
beer hall push of 1923.
However, fate dealt them a favorable
hand. the post-war economic recovery
under the Vhimmer Republic, which was
genuine enough while it lasted, that had
collapsed as a direct result of the Wall
Street crash in New York.
It
>> was a saying of the time, [music] New
York sneezed, London caught cold, and
Germany nearly died of influenza.
The implications of the crash would
eventually lead the National Socialist
Party to total power.
>> The continuity of the Great Depression
was absolutely critical. 7 million men
became unemployed. There seemed to be no
lifting. And once you got the worker in
the do, you had him as a potential Nazi,
a potential stormtrooper.
What further measures would be imposed
on the German population to consolidate
the Nazis power? And what terror would
be unleashed before the dramatic
toppling of this evil regime?
>> [snorts]
>> World War I had left Germany. In a state
of shock,
2 million fatalities, spiraling
inflation, and unpaid debts to the
Allied countries caused the nation to
feel stripped of its identity and pride.
They felt that the Allies had deceived
them, had abandoned all notions of honor
by treating them as a conquered people.
>> Hitler was a war hero. He won the Iron
Cross first class. The First World War
turned a nobody into a somebody.
>> Adolf Hitler had survived the conflict
and found a political home in the German
Workers Party, a right-wing [music]
organization with racist and
anti-semitic roots.
Hitler, like many others, had to find
some way of explaining it [music] to
himself. And like tens of thousands of
others, he blamed socialists, Marxist,
Jews, people that undermined Germany
[music] from within.
Climbing the ranks, he changed the name
to the National Socialist German Workers
Party and took control.
As leader, he started [music] plotting
the takeover of Munich and in turn
Germany.
>> The infamous beer [__] push was a
resounding failure.
>> It was built up into an iconic episode
in the history of the movement.
>> Hitler was arrested, put on trial.
>> Hitler was later imprisoned. His
intentions, however, were still for
total power and to return the nation to
a state of pride. Hitler knew that he
would need a different approach.
>> First of all, he had to get the army,
police, civil service, and business on
his side. And secondly, he had to
develop a propaganda apparatus which
would win votes.
>> If we can't outshoot them, we'll [music]
outvote them. And we'll do it by winning
support.
He would fuse violent acts of terror
with slick propaganda, which would all
fuel this fatal attraction.
In the late 1920s, the Nazi party found
themselves with diminishing support as
the German economy became stronger.
In 1928, Germany was in quite reasonable
circumstances. There had been a recovery
from the depression after the war,
recovery from the inflation with the
stabilization of the currency in [music]
1924. The economy appeared to be
booming.
This was largely because there was an
enormous influx of [music] American
money.
The Germans spent a lot of the loan
money on things that were very desirable
like concert halls and [music] swimming
pools and so on, but they weren't
productive. So, Germany looked as if it
was prospering.
>> Unforeseen events in the world economy
would end up having huge ramifications
for Germany.
post-war economic recovery under the
VHimar Republic, which was genuine
enough while it lasted, that had
collapsed. That had gone into free fall
as a direct result of the Wall Street
crash in New York.
>> October 29th, 1929,
Black Tuesday, the New York Stock
Exchange is in a panic. Frantic
investors have scrambled to unload their
stocks at any price. Everyone wants to
sell. No one wants to buy. Suddenly,
even the most guilted securities are
practically valueless. The stock market
crash has come and the Great Depression
has begun.
>> They just pulled the rug out from
Germany. They just withdrew their
investments.
>> American banks withdrew the loans on
which a German recovery after the
hyperinflation of 1923 had depended.
[music] German banks collapsed. They
withdrew their money from businesses.
businesses collapsed.
>> So many of the loans particularly had
been made on a 14-day basis. They could
just withdraw them. So the German
economy contracted very suddenly, very
quickly.
>> Every European country was affected.
Germany was disastrously affected.
>> There was a saying of the time, New York
sneezed, London caught cold, and Germany
nearly died of influenza. It really was
first and foremost a crisis of
industrial society
and the major unemployment was in
industry particularly the building
trade.
>> By 1932
there was 35 to 40% unemployment in
Germany.
>> That is how catastrophic [music] the
depression was. When you throw manual
workers out of jobs, of course, the
people who are the clarks in these
occupations suffer as well.
>> The continuity of the Great Depression
was absolutely critical. And once you
got the worker in the do, you had him as
a potential Nazi, a potential [music]
stormtrooper.
The people of Germany were down and out.
and the now called National Socialist
Party had found a cause to champion that
would increase their visibility and
popularity
>> in that atmosphere of crisis when
governments were only able to rule by
decree because the parties couldn't get
together and get behind a policy to deal
with this massive economic collapse. In
that situation, people voters thought
this is the last straw. We've had
hyperinflation. [music] We've had
international humiliation. We've got
political chaos. The Nazis seem to be
the one party that's led by youthful,
determined, energetic [music]
individuals.
They promoted the party actually in 1930
[music] particularly as the Hitler
movement, the Hitler Beum. This of
course was after Hitler had had the ban
on his public speaking lifted and so he
had been going around speaking a great
deal.
>> It's very difficult to find anything to
which the party was willing to commit
[music] itself.
>> They were very very vague on what they
intended to do. They seem to have to
offer something to every constituency in
Germany. the worker, uh, the manager,
the low middle class women. [music]
>> What he was saying in one place wasn't
necessarily compatible with what he was
saying elsewhere in in terms of, say,
economic detail.
>> We're going to make Germany great again.
We're going to recover. We're going to
have work for everybody. Uh, we'll put
Germany back on the international scene.
We're going to rescue the German family.
will give German women uh a much better
life. These are all cliches and when you
probe they really don't have any
particular policies that they can
actually present in a rational way to
the general public.
>> Much of it rested simply on that Germany
will be rescued. Germany will [music]
become a great power and Hitler will be
the person to achieve it.
Electoral success would come to the
Nazis at the beginning of the 1930s and
their popularity continued to rise as
the population grew more disillusioned
with the established government.
I think that the electoral success of
Hitler's party [music] in 1932
didn't necessarily reflect the strengths
of the party itself or its ideological
appeal. [music] It really reflected the
extraordinary crisis that Germany had
gone through as a result of the Wall
Street [music] crash. And I think what a
lot of German people did was they
desperately looked around for some kind
of messiah. And that's how Hitler was
being sold to the public. Their appeal
was many sided and of course their
vision was of what they called a folks
gain shaft a folk community in which the
party could represent all social classes
and groups. Hitler stands for election
as president in April 1932
against Hindenburg who had been
president since 1925 [music]
and he loses but he comes second. He
comes a [music] prettyable second and
it's given him a much higher profile
than he'd previously had. The propaganda
continues [music] and in the uh uh
election of July 1932,
the Nazi party gets 37% of the vote
[music]
and is the largest single party in the
Reich with 230 seats, more than doubling
its 1930 total. That's a tremendous
success. But Hitler is not offered the
chancellorship. Actually, it was his
democratic right to be offered the
chancellorship, but he is not.
He is offered the vice chancellorship
and he turns it down.
>> A large proportion of the middle class
voted for the National Socialist Party
in the July elections of 1932 as a
protest to the Hindenburg government. By
November they had retracted their
support.
>> There is another election in November
and the Nazi vote declines to 33%. still
I think 196 seats in in in the rashtag
but uh it's a matter of considerable
disappointment [music]
to a lot of followers.
>> So what do they do? They seem to be uh
on the verge of their death cough, their
death rattle.
>> There is now not such a pressing need to
offer Hitler the chancellorship. Local
election votes and so on at the time are
showing [music] a decline in the Nazi
vote. I mean they might just have
fizzled out. There is then a minor
election in the state of Lippy [music]
and what the Nazis do is flood it with
their marketing resource. They throw
everything at this miniature state of
Lippy and they win. And it's at that
point that Hindenburg finally invites
Hitler to be part of a coalition
government.
>> The small cry of conservative
politicians decided they could
manipulate Hitler, offered him the
chancellorship uh and that was the
start. Adolf Hitler, leader of the
German national movement, is made
chancellor of Germany and Berlin goes
wild in celebration of his victory.
[cheering]
>> Having secured the role as [music] Reich
Chancellor, it took one more twist of
fate in favor of the National Socialists
to see the future of Germany take a
deadly turn and hand Hitler complete
control.
The Wall Street crash had sent Germany
into economic crisis. The nation was
subjected to a second wave of spiraling
inflation and soaring unemployment.
However, it gave the National Socialist
Party the means to win a large
proportion of the vote in a relatively
short space of time.
In January 1933, Hitler was appointed
Reich Chancellor. His plan of total
power was almost tangible.
4 weeks later on February 27th, 1933 at
9:25 p.m. an alarm call was taken in a
Berlin fire station. Fire had broken out
in the Reichdark building, the home of
the German Parliament. By 11:30 p.m.,
the fire was extinguished, but had left
the building a gutted shell. On
searching the smoldering ruin, a young
Dutch communist, Marinus Vanuba, was
found. He was arrested for starting the
fire. According to police, he acted out
of rebellion, a call for the German
workers to rise up against the
oppression of fascism. The Nazis [music]
saw the Communist Party as a huge threat
to national socialism and also knew that
a large proportion of the German
population was suspicious of the far
left. Stalin having come to power late
1920s, [music]
you have the first 5-year plan in 1928.
You [music] have collectivization
starting in 1929.
word gets back about what it [music]
means
and the last thing German peasants want
is collectivization. A lot of German
peasants, a lot of small holders, they
don't want collectivization. [music]
Neither do the big land owners.
>> The fire allowed Hitler to pass two sets
of legislation. The first of which was
the Riceark fire decree. This was drawn
up the day after the incident and signed
by President Hindenburg. The decree
allowed the enforced imprisonment
[music]
of anyone opposed to the Nazi regime and
action to be taken against any
publication deemed [music] critical of
the cause. The decree led to the
enabling act passed in parliament on
March 23rd, 1933.
It gave the Nazi party power to [music]
enforce laws without the intervention of
the Reichards.
Passing of the enabling act essentially
handed power to Hitler and the National
Socialist Party. They immediately let it
be known throughout Germany.
Fritz Lustig, a Jewish immigrant who now
resides in North London, was living in
Berlin in 1933.
>> I was born in 1919. I had a very happy
childhood. I was the youngest of four
siblings and I had a very happy time at
school. Although I experienced the uh
Nazis coming to power. We were
rehearsing for a play at school and
suddenly we heard uh Marshall music
sounding and we looked out of the window
and there was a Nazi demonstration
passing with lit torches and a band at
the at the head of the procession. We
read in the papers the next day that
there had been similar positions all
over Berlin and we just had been
happening to watch the one which took
place in that particular part of town.
The national election of March 1933 saw
the National Socialist Party take 43% of
the vote, but they still failed to win a
majority.
Unbeknownst to the German population,
this would be the last democratic
election until World War II.
>> So people still thought in March, April
1933 [music]
that the democratic system was not dead,
but it was. We look at it backwards. We
can [music] see what happened.
People even say, "Why did all these
people vote for a party [music] that
unleashed war and genocide?" Well, they
didn't know that's what they were going
to do.
>> The Nazis had taken Germany by lawful
means. Hitler's plan had worked. And
although his party had still not managed
to gain a majority, they had total
power. They believed there was still an
enemy who may stand in the way of this
domination that would come from within
the party [music] itself. The
termination of this enemy would
culminate on July 2nd, 1934.
The incident known as the night of the
long knives would see the murder of Erns
Rum, the head of the Sturmab Tailong.
>> Hitler and the party leadership had
arrived at the point where they felt
they had to take on the SA the map
Tylum.
>> Various [music] senior paladins of the
Reich feared the power of Rome. They
coveted it for themselves, specifically
Himmler. And so they began to tell
Hitler that Rome was plotting against
him, which was not in fact true. The
army hated them because they're rival
source of power. I think from Hitler's
point of view, the real problem was that
he he was worried that Rome really would
develop a popular following, more
popular perhaps in the [music] end than
the following for Hitler. There's a real
distrust about Rome's motives [music]
and Rome's political ambitions.
>> Rome is very definitely number two to
Hitler and therefore as some saw it a
potential rival uh to his power and they
had a readymade weapon and that was the
SS the shoots.
The SS were originally a small battalion
of the much larger SA but in 1929
Hinrich Himmler was appointed leader and
taking inspiration [music] from Rome
began to rapidly expand the unit.
Initially they were Hitler's bodyguard
but by 1933 after the seizure of power
it became the internal security of the
Nazi regime. By 1934, they were growing
into a real and formidable private army,
equipped
famously with their black uniforms,
black helmets, with their own weaponry,
and they did much of the business when
Hitler decided it was time to move
[music] against the SA.
Using falsified evidence, Himmler had
assembled a file which cited that R had
been paid 12 million Deutsch marks by
France to overthrow Hitler. In addition
to this, R's homosexuality was used as a
way of discrediting him. He and others
in the SA leadership were accused of
acts of drunkenness and deborttery. This
was used as a way of excusing the action
which Hitler was about to take.
So it was an easy matter to set them up
with allegations of internal corruption
particularly of homosexuality and it was
a chance to settle a lot of old scores.
On the morning of June 30th, Hitler with
a large number of SS marched into the
hotel in Bard Visay where Rum and many
leaders of the SA were staying. They
were arrested at gunpoint and later
executed.
It was a brutal business. When the move
was made, essay were taken totally by
surprise and much of their leadership
was was wiped out. With the brutal
execution of Rome and other potential
opponents, Hitler sent a clear message
to all that opposition would not be
tolerated. The Jewish population and
those on the left were already living
with constant persecution. Yet, the Nazi
party's popularity amongst the German
nation grew. The threat of violence,
intelligent propaganda, and the complete
[music] monopoly of all institutions in
Germany gave people no choice but to
support.
>> The National Socialist Party had not won
a majority in any of the elections of
the early 1930s.
However, the passing of the enabling act
saw Hitler gain complete control [music]
of Germany.
In turn, the knight of the long lies had
killed off any potential [music]
political threat he may have had.
The German nation found themselves
living under a dictatorship.
Jews, communists, social democrats were
all targeted as enemies of the state.
Persecution, imprisonment, and
systematic execution were all threats to
these members of society.
Working closely with Hitler, it was
Joseph Gerbles who saw to it that the
veneer of the Nazi party would appeal to
the masses.
This campaign intensified once power had
been consolidated,
but its roots were set long before.
The selfimage that they wanted to create
was of a movement of youth.
>> The existing politicians were all in
their 50s and 60s. The Nazis are in
their 20s and 30s.
>> The embodiment of all the energies of a
new Germany, a new uncorrupted
generation.
>> The one party that's led by youthful,
determined, energetic [music]
individuals.
>> The Hitler Yungant or Hitler Youth were
the personification of the Nazi image
and gave the National Socialists a
vibrant youthful image.
Because Hitler believes that too much
education is dangerous, the young Nazi
gets his only schooling after working
hours, a daily lecture on Germany's need
for expansion, and the triumph he will
share when German armies march into the
rich wheat fields of the Russian
Ukraine.
The Hitler Youth eventually became
almost uh compulsory. Uh the Nazis
market them very very heavily. In other
words, what we'd imagine them to be as a
rigidly a hierarchical organization
[music] with cruel discipline and
bullying and so forth is not actually
how they're self-presented. They're
actually self-presented as a kind of
adventure holiday.
>> At 18, every young man must serve 6
months in the Arbite.
>> There was one boy in my form whom I
quite liked who was in the Hitler youth.
I was very keen on associating with him.
I think he was less keen uh to associate
with me.
>> The man who was first given charge of
it. Balder fun was an able organizer
good at recruiting. But the real takeoff
was only after the Nazis took power.
Within 18 months they were able to claim
3 and a half million uh members. And
that doesn't count of course the women's
and girls organizations that were set up
in parallel to it.
>> The girls organization was called bunt
deer maid the league of German girls.
>> There a lot of young people who
gravitated to the Hitler movement
actually then influenced their parents
not the other way around.
>> It wasn't just youth groups that were
monopolized by the Nazi party. All
organizations [music] were in turn
affected.
>> The Nazis forced every single voluntary
society [music] or organization in
Germany to join the Nazi party or become
part of a Nazi apparatus.
That meant all orchestras, opera houses,
singing clubs, amateur dramatic
societies, all of that, they had to
become part of the Reich Chamber of
Culture, which is under the propaganda
ministry. And of course, if you wanted
to [music] practice
art and exhibit your work, you had
[music] to be admitted to the Chamber of
Culture. And if you're Jewish, you
wouldn't be admitted. If you're a modern
artist, you [music] wouldn't be
admitted. So, this is a way of imposing
control.
>> All aspects of life were effectively
taken over by the National Socialists.
These changes were witnessed [music] by
the school child Fritz Lustig.
We had a new headmaster. Our current
headmaster was not Jewish, but he was a
social democrat and therefore his
politics were not acceptable to the
Nazis. And a new headmaster was
appointed. He introduced several new uh
measures. Uh one of them was that uh the
uh weekly Monday morning assembly was
completely transformed after everybody
had sat down. Uh, one of the boys who
was stationed at the entrance door
shouted, "Akong, attention." And then
the headmaster walked in along the
central aisle all through the hall with
his arm outstretched in the Hitler
salute, turned smartly round when he
reached the podium, shouted, "Hitler,
and the whole school had to answer with
the same."
I suppose I must have outstretched my
hand in the hitter salute that because
not to do that would have drawn
attention to me. I didn't want to draw
attention to myself by raising the
question of whether I was excluded.
Today the Nazi propaganda machine is
seeking to make Adolf Hitler the only
god of the German people out to destroy
every established religionism. As the
party took control of all areas of
society and permeated into the lives of
every German citizen, the need for
greater, more effective propaganda
became paramount. [music]
There was uh nothing which wasn't
propaganda of one sort or another. Every
[music] surface was interrogated for its
propaganda potential.
The press was censored and Nazi
newspapers [music]
really had the lion's share of
circulation.
The folks fanger, the people's radio,
was an affordable device manufactured on
the orders of Joseph Gerbles. More
people owning radios meant a larger
audience for propaganda. the propaganda
barrage to confuse to make them lose
faith, to divide and conquer.
>> To lull the fears of the little
neutrals, propaganda minister Gerbles
told them Germany didn't want a war at
all. It was Britain and France that
caused all the trouble.
>> Radio was taken over and there was a
Reich broadcasting [music]
company and radio of course was
dominated completely by
state output. 70% of German homes owned
a radio. By 1939,
>> there were loudspeakers installed on
lamposts and in trees. And when uh any
of these features took place, of course,
you were expected to stand still and
listen to them.
>> Film production was taken over by the
Nazis as well. Yoseph Gerbles was very
[music] much aware of the fact that
people would get bored very quickly if
they were subjected to constant barrage
of propaganda about how wonderful the
Nazis were. He was rather upset when
Hitler commissioned a propaganda film of
the Neurember party rally in 1934 from a
young actress Lenny Reefenstein.
[music]
Triumph of the Will was a film directed
by Lenny Reefenstyle which documents the
1934 Nuremberg rally. Its main themes
are unity and returning power to
Germany. It was no mistake that Nazi
symbolism and imagery are prominent
throughout the film. Hitler understood
the power of the Nazi brand.
>> You actually have a core brand symbol
system. You have obviously the swastika,
you have the stylized eagle. Uh you have
the other things like the [music] oak
leaves, the acorns. Then of course
there's the uniforms. I once counted up
the number of uniforms in Nazi Germany
about 150. These uniforms were highly
symbolic. For example, the SS uniforms
were vaguely modeled on the Death's Head
Haz of German history, which was a black
uniform with the Scarland [music]
crossbones and the the Stark silver.
This was a way of boosting morale, of
boosting identity, of of priming
solidarity. [music]
The brown shirts were the first
organization uh to be costumed by Hugo
Boss. I mean, it's just impossible to
imagine, in fact, almost any other
historical leader in history going to a
[music] catwalk showing of new clothes
for the soldiers, only Hitler. And for
reasons [music] unique to him and unique
to the Third Reich,
the National Socialists found success in
running both wellplanned propaganda and
brutal acts of violence simultaneously.
[music]
However, it was the Olympic Games of
1936 which would see a halt to the
terror and the suppression of
anti-semitism.
Hitler understood the power of the games
and exploited them in order to show
Europe and the rest of the world a false
image of a peaceful, tolerant Germany.
Captain Eric Brown was a spectator at
the games along with his father. It was
clear that the Nazi propaganda machine
was sending out the message it desired.
But it was a black American athlete who
stole the show.
I was 17 when we went to the Olympics.
It was a wonderful occasion. And of
course to me the highlight at that time
was to see this wonderful athlete Jesse
Owens
[cheering]
who wins it ahead and fighting Kansas
>> who won the 100 m or 200 m 100 m and the
long jump quite incredible he was poetry
in motion
>> the lanky car from Ohio State shatters
all existing records as he takes the
gold medal in the men's broad jump with
a sensational leap of 26 ft 5 and 516 in
Owens in particular was staggered by his
reception in Germany as he got off the
boat wherever he went [cheering]
the crowds chanted Ovenans Owens all
over the place and for a brief time an
American black man was more popular in
Nazi Germany than Adolf Hitler himself
The Olympics had placed Hitler in a
favorable light throughout the world.
However, once the games were over, the
Nazis would renew their persecution. The
Jewish population would soon face a
greater terror than they had ever
previously suffered.
The 1936 [music]
Olympics allowed Hitler to project to
the world a vision of a tolerant,
[music] progressive nation.
His popularity within Germany was also
rising. Those parts of the nation who
were not seen as a threat were being
shown that the Nazi party would deliver
on the promises they made. But as with
all aspects of the regime, there was a
more sinister subplot.
The thing that had led people to vote
had been the unemployment problem of the
early 1930s and the promise that the
Nazis would solve that. Well, they did
with a vengeance.
>> If anybody was unemployed or they were
rounded up and uh made for example to
chop wood which was given to the elderly
or the very poor. Certainly by 1938
there there were 400,000
unemployed in Germany. I mean it is
nothing. But there were always offers to
um tempt them to join the Nazi party.
You join the ranks, be paid, be
uniformed seemed quite attractive.
Although it seemed that the whole nation
was behind them, the main anti-semitic
[music] message of the Jewish conspiracy
was still being played out by the
department of propaganda.
>> The idea of a Jewish world conspiracy
was not one that was present in more
than a very tiny fragment of the German
population.
>> They were successful in business up to a
point. They controlled [music] some of
the big departmental stores in Germany.
But in no sense were they in control
of the life of the Vhimar state.
In every village, in every town and city
are stormtroopers from whose
headquarters the local party leader
directs his district campaign of terror,
marks victims for persecution.
Hitler was keen on keeping the
suppression of Jews at the forefront of
Nazi policy as Germany and the German
nation were historically not known for
their anti-semitism.
It had been the place that many Jews had
gone [music] to from countries that
genuinely were anti-semitic. Uh the
strong anti-semitic tradition in [music]
in Austria, strong anti-semitism in
Romania. Uh Soviet anti-semitism was
always kept under [music] wraps, but it
was certainly there. and of course
Polish anti-semitism where a very large
proportion of Europe's students lived.
>> A young Eric Brown teaching in Germany
could see from an [music] objective
point of view the effect of the Nazis
anti-semitic policies.
I was very aware of the fact that
[music] the Nazi regime was building up
into a very very [music] clamorous
political body
and a very ruthless political body too.
>> The Nazis began to unroll then their own
brand of anti-semitism, radical
anti-semitism. There was an evil aspect,
if you like to put it that way, [music]
to the Nazi regime.
>> On November 7th, 1938, Erns Fomrath, a
German diplomat in Paris, was shot by
Hershel Grinspan, a young German Jewish
man. His motive was a direct response to
Nazi anti-semitism.
Two days later, Vomrath was pronounced
dead. Orders were given to the SA and SS
to take to the streets and destroy all
Jewishowned property and businesses
[music] and arrest all Jewish men. The
following two nights were an
orchestrated and systematic series of
attacks on Jews [music] throughout
Germany. It would become known as
Crystal.
91 Jews died and 300,000 were arrested
and sent [music] to concentration camps.
On November 9th, after a chamber [music]
music performance in which he was
playing cello, Fritz Lustig returned
home.
>> When I reached home, I saw that there
was a great crowd in front of the
entrance to the uh building where our
flat was situated. The window had been
smashed and the people outside the shop
was having themselves freely to any
alcohol alcoholic drinks that were
there. I went up to our flat unmolested,
was told by my parents that this crowd
had been there for some time and they
hadn't set in fact set fire to the shop.
Fritz and his father found hideouts at
two different houses in the suburbs of
Berlin. Neither faced arrest, but the
events of Crystal Knuck were immediately
felt.
There were too many Jewish men in Berlin
to arrest them all because in the
provinces we knew that there had been no
exemptions.
I went to my office the next morning. It
was a Jewish owned firm and when I
arrived I was told that both our boss
and his two sons had been arrested and
put put into concentration camps. When I
went to the bank, the cashier asked me
whether it was true as he had heard that
my boss had been arrested. And I said,
"Yes, it was true." And he shook his
head and said, and I always thought he
was an honest man.
>> I think the German population obviously
knew it because it was there happening
in front of their eyes. But to them, the
stakes were so high in getting their
pride back. I think about 80% of them
were prepared to put up with anything if
they could be become what they wanted to
be, a proud nation once again.
Hitler commanded his popularity amongst
the German nation through a series of
nonviolent territory gains in the latter
half of [music] the 1930s.
>> Most Germans are terribly anxious. They
do not want another war. They're afraid
that their cities will be bombed. They
don't want to go through another first
world war. So there's huge relief when
the various crises of the
remilitarization, the rhinand in 1936,
Angelus of Austria 1938, the Czechlovac
crisis, they're all solved uh basically
without without bloodshed. That gains
Hitler a reputation, popularity in
Germany, but not because he's being
militaristic. His idea is [music] to
refight this first world war, but on a
better basis. So his aim very early on
is to conquer uh Eastern Europe, [music]
use it as a kind of bread basket as a
source of supplies because one of the
reasons why Germany lost in 1914 to 18
is because Germany did not have enough
supplies. More than half a million
Germans died from starvation on
malnutrition in the first world war. So
he wants to write [music] that wrong.
Although Hitler was remilitarizing at an
unprecedented rate, the German nation
nor the rest of the world could [music]
see war on the horizon.
We did not know how close war was going
to be. We did know that the Nazis had
started rearming very soon after they
came to power.
>> All the other [music] great powers
realized that Germany was rearming in
the 1930s. It was secret of course till
35 and declared openly they had good
intelligence on what was going on. But
on the other hand, I think a great many
politicians abroad thought it was a bad
idea to disarm Germany anyway. A modest
rearm might satisfy German ambitions.
They would allow Germany back into the
family of nations again.
>> Everybody who was anti-Nazi thought that
the allies would take steps to prevent
further rearmament, but they never did.
The only reason I can think of why they
didn't do it because there was a great
anti-war feeling in all those countries.
None of the populations in Britain,
France or Poland wanted a war to happen.
>> I knew there'd be trouble, but not I
certainly didn't think all about war.
After the events of [music] Crystal
Knuck, thousands of Jews had been forced
to immigrate and those that hadn't
realized it was time to leave.
After the events of November 1938, it
became obvious to everybody, including
my parents, [music] that to stay in
Germany might be termed suicide because
one could no longer be sure that was
one's life was not in danger.
Fritz Lustik's parents managed to find
refuge [music] in Portugal where his
eldest sister lived. As war became
inevitable, [music] Eric Brown had no
choice in leaving. I was asleep on the
Sunday morning at the 3rd of September
when there was a thunderous knock at the
door. When I opened it, there were two
SS
officers said, "Our countries are at
war." Which was technically incorrect at
[music] 6:00 in the morning cuz it
wasn't till 11:00 we were at war. But I
didn't think that was a very strong
point to argue. And um the SS chap said,
"Uh, you'll have to come with us, so get
dressed and um get ready."
Eric Brown was detained for 3 days and
then dropped [music] at the Swiss
border. From here he made his way back
to Britain where he immediately signed
up to the war effort.
Having stayed in England in 1936, Fritz
Lustig found refuge with the Quaker
family with whom [music] he had lodged.
When I immigrated that was on a
transatlantic steamer which was going
from Hamburg via Sherbor and France and
Southampton and England. We interlanded
in Sherbor and this was the first time I
was able to walk about without being
aware of having to look over my shoulder
to see whether anybody was listening to
what I said. In other words, to feel
free. And that was a marvelous feeling
which I remember to this day.
>> In just 10 years, Hitler and the Nazis
had moved from a marginal fascist party
with a small following into a military
dictatorship ready to wage fullcale war.
The promise of rebuilding Germany and
reinstating pride to the nation fueled
Hitler's popularity despite acts of
savage violence that left thousands dead
and a great deal more seeking refuge in
other countries. When the curtain was
raised on the theater of combat, Germany
rallied behind their furer.
The victory over Poland was certainly
welcomed because it it writed the wrong
as people saw it of the territorial
settlement at the end of the First World
War. I think most Germans would have
been very happy to leave it at that. The
high point of Hitler's popularity was
undoubtedly in the summer of 1940 after
the very rapid conquest with relatively
little [music]
bloodshed. The victories of 1939 1940
created what proved to be a shortlived
period of absolute
mass euphoria in Germany. One victory
after another. All of this is ecstasy
because the prophet is what he says he
is. He is real. He is an earthly god by
this stage. And of course the trouble is
he begins to believe his own mythology.
The beginning of the Second World
[music] War would see the decline of
Nazi support.
It would take a costly and bloody war to
end [music] this horrific regime.
Heat. Heat.
>> [screaming and cheering]
>> In 1933, Adolf Hitler was made
chancellor of Germany. This allowed the
Nazi regime to seize complete power. The
Wall Street crash, the rice dog fire,
and the death of Erns vonra all enabled
the Nazis to further their tyranny.
German military rearmament was
prioritized and in 1935, the Vermacht
saw its reincarnation following the
disarmament after World War I.
Britain and France turned a blind eye to
this contravention of the Versai treaty.
The German people were excited by the
prospect of the country becoming great
again.
Exploiting all aspects of the media,
Joseph Gerbles masterminded the slick
propaganda which was fed to the
population.
>> Gerbles's great insight [music] was that
the best propaganda is disguised as
something else. It's carried on the back
of entertainment.
Coupled with this, the violent
persecution of all those opposed to the
regime became progressively worse.
>> A strong powerful street presence,
unformed marching men and boys and a lot
of them. The repetitive power [music] of
violent brutal street theater when it
came to dealing with opposition. Terror
played a very important part in
mediatorship throughout its entire
length. No political descent would be
tolerated.
The Nazi party delivered on their
promise of higher employment. And
although the German nation was not
oblivious to the violence and
persecution, they allowed it to continue
in the hope that Hitler would restore
their pride.
>> The only real long-term aims were to
stay in power, win back territory for
Germany, and to win back respect for
Germany. I knew there was a lot of
unrest, but I didn't think it would
blossom into allout war.
>> The Second World War would see the
height of Nazi popularity, but it would
also be their ultimate downfall.
>> His idea is to refight the First World
War, but on a better basis. His aim very
early on is to conquer Eastern Europe.
Once it became [music] clear that
victory was not going to be easy, then a
great many German people realized that
this had been a gamble and that they'd
lost.
>> He maintained [music]
his faith because it was a matter of
will.
>> He'd come to believe that he [music] was
a messiah blessed by providence. He just
believed that there was something of the
divine about him.
To fully understand the outbreak of
World War II, we have to look back to
1936 and the start of the Nazi
reoccupation of land lost from the
Versailles treaty.
>> One of the fundamental principles of the
treaty of Versailles had been national
self-determination.
Every nation [music] should have its
state. So the Hz monik being broken up,
the Austrians, Hungarians, the checks,
Yugoslavs, they [music] got their own.
Why should this be denied to the
Germans?
Hitler certainly sets out an agenda for
moving into the Rhineland which had
become a demilitarized zone under the
terms of the Versailles treaty.
>> German soldiers again breaking a treaty
marched into the demilitarized
Rhineland.
The Rhyland was sovereign German
territory. It's a remilitarization. It's
having military installations on it. It
had been occupied up to 1930. The deal
was that the Germans would have it under
their own control, that the occupation
forces would leave, but that there would
be no military installations in it.
1936, of course, uh Hitler sends his
troops into the Rhineland and big
military show.
[screaming]
On March 12th, 1938, the German army
marched into Austria. They were met with
cheering crowds as they crossed the
border. Hitler's appeal was growing
rapidly.
The Anloo is popular with a lot of
people in Austria. Perhaps not as many
as it looks because the previous regime
of Dulus and Shushnig had done the work
for Hitler by banning the left in 1934.
The Social Democrats had been banned.
They were underground. So there's no
opposition really in Austria either. I
mean, it's a dictatorship as well.
Hitler said that he had no desire on any
territory which had not had a historical
memory of a German presence. The Germans
were a pan European tribe. They were not
a nation in a country [music] as the
rest of us really are. They were
everywhere. They are not in the Iberian
Peninsula. They were not in the British
Isles, but they were everywhere else
stretching deep into Russia. So there's
no resistance in Europe to the German
takeover of German speakaking Austria.
The German demand for the incorporation
of 2 million German speakers on the
western boundaries of Czechoslovakia in
1938 is exceeded to because it fulfills
that principle.
On September 30th, 1938, Germany,
France, Britain, and Italy signed the
Munich Agreement, which attempted to
appease Hitler's designs on
Czechoslovakia following the Angelus of
Austria.
>> Meanwhile, at Munich, misguided
statesmen were lulled into believing
that Hitler would cage his stormtroopers
in return for a sizable [music] hunk of
Czechoslovakia. They signed away the
Sudatan land in a move to appease a
rattlesnake. a rattlesnake who having
once flooded himself on the [music] rich
food of another nation's lands would
become ravenously hungry again and
again.
>> The agreement handed Hitler the Sudatan
land area of Czechoslovakia which left
the country weakened and on March 16th
Germany took control of the country.
>> I think it may be true that Hitler
[music] felt he had been cheated off his
war over the Sudatan land. He had a
peculiar hatred for the checks. [music]
I'm not entirely sure why. Maybe it was
just checks and poles as [music] Slavs.
It seems as if he may have felt denied a
war in the autumn of 1938 at [music] a
time when he felt his potential
adversaries were too weak. really
>> the remilitarization of the Rhineland
Angelus of Austria 1938 the Czechoslovak
crisis they're all solved uh basically
without without bloodshed that gains
Hitler reputation and popularity in
Germany but not because he's [music]
being militaristic
>> the sequence of territory gains made by
the Nazis in the late 1930s won back the
majority of land lost by the signing of
the Versai treaty after the first world
war.
>> Winning the foreign policy successes
[music] of the 1930s without having to
resort to war was a major gain that was
appreciated by a lot of people and
restore German pride in a in a big way.
The turning point only comes in March
1939 when Hitler marches into the rest
of Tekkavia which is inhabited not by
Germans but by checks. At that point
there's a general realization in
political elites in other countries in
Europe that he's after more than simply
[music]
recreating a kind of German nation
state. Hitler gambled on the fact they'd
get away with doing these things without
war and his gambling instinct served him
well. The Britain, France, the western
democracies did not respond militarily
for all kinds of reasons. The real
gamble was 1939 when it came to the move
against Poland.
>> Signed in 1939 in Moscow, the
non-aggression pact would establish Nazi
Germany and Russia as allies. By then he
knew [music] he could get away with it
or he did by early August after the
extraordinary turnaround in the Reich's
policy of signing a mutual
non-aggression pact with the Soviet
Union. That was the moment at which the
field was cleared for Hitler to move
against Poland.
>> Germany invades Poland and the pre-state
of Danzi. The efforts and hopes of
diplomats for peaceful settlement are
transformed into the roar of gunfire.
Warsaw is bombed, blasted, and shelled.
Poland is in ruin.
>> Where the gamble went wrong was that
Britain and France honored their treaty
obligations to Poland. Hitler had never
thought they would do that.
>> The eve of war was upon the German
nation. It would be a conflict which
would bring about the demise of the Nazi
regime, but it would also facilitate
mass genocide, brutal murder, and
bloodshed on a scale which no one could
have imagined possible.
Territory
gains made by the Nazi regime were
carried out with minimum of bloodshed
and resistance. The German nation was
buoyant. Their furer was delivering.
>> War has struck again.
>> However, on September 1st, 1939, Germany
invaded Poland.
With regard to the Treaty of Versailles,
this attack proved a step too far for
Britain and the Allies.
>> I have to tell you now, this country is
at war with Germany.
>> The Second World War had commenced.
>> The wrong of Versailles had been writed.
They hadn't got Alzas Loren back. They
could live without them. The Polish
corridor was the big issue
territorially.
They had that. [music] They had Austria.
People would have been very happy to
leave it at that. But the war was not
concluded.
And you you do get complaints even in
the autumn of 1939.
This war has been going on too long.
>> In the winter of 1939, Hitler would
unleash his blitzkrieg upon Western
Europe. And over the following months,
Germany would go on to conquer many more
countries.
>> One victory after another. The fall of
uh France, the fall of Belgium, the fall
of Holland, the fall of Norway. All of
this is a kind of ecstasy.
>> I think the euphoria is partly that now
it really is all over and we we've done
really well. People were pretty pleased
with [music] that. and Hitler been done
under his leadership. So he got a lot of
credit for that.
>> The prophet is what he says he is. He is
real. He is an earthly god by this
stage. And of course the trouble is he
begins to believe his own mythology.
>> Very rapid conquest with relatively
little bloodshed, not much loss on the
German side. Very short war. All of this
was treated with huge enthusiasm by the
German people, partly because they then
thought the war would come to an end.
>> That was certainly enough for
the overwhelming majority of Germans.
>> I think that all those crowds you see in
the news fields waving flags and
screaming, it's all true. I mean, they
couldn't believe it that in a few weeks
they defeated an enemy they couldn't
defeat in four years of grueling war.
Hitler was one of the few people in
Germany who welcomed another war. He
wasn't scared. The First World War had
made him somebody. But for other
Germans, 2 million German men had been
killed during the First World War. And
an awful lot had been wounded. You just
had to look at the the maimed
ex-servicemen on the streets. [snorts]
So it was a terrible prospect for an
awful lot of people.
In a drive as speedy as that to the
channel, Nazi units pushed southward and
rapidly outflanked the famous French
Majino line.
Following the French surrender, [music]
Hitler arranged for the armistice
between Germany and France to be signed
in the same train carriage [music] in
the same location which 22 years
previously had been used for the signing
of the armistice [music]
of 1918.
Reaching the English Channel in May 1940
and outmaneuvering the British, causing
the retreat to Dunkirk, the German army
looked to be the far superior aggressor.
Britain was on the brink of seeking
terms with Germany, but Winston
Churchill argued that nations which went
down fighting rose again, but those
which surrendered tamely were finished.
Hitler gave a rather empty speech
offering peace terms which weren't very
specified to Britain. And when Churchill
rejected them, it was universal outrage
and incomprehension [music] in Germany.
Churchill knew that a peace with Germany
at that point would mean German control
over Britain would get greater and
greater. He would probably be ousted.
[music] Fascists like Mosley would
become the U. Prime Minister. uh that it
would be in effect a a surrender in
stages. Uh he was quite right [music] to
reject this very vague peace offer. But
an interesting [music] aspect of this is
his view of Churchill whom he respected
as a fellow artist. And for a long time
his plan for Churchill in the event of
German victory was to just leave him in
a country house uh where he could paint
and not spring him up [music] like all
the others or put him in a concentration
camp.
Trying to bomb Britain into submission
over the winter of 1940 1941 was a huge
miscalculation. They did not have the
offensive air power to do it.
>> Hello America. This is Edward Merl
speaking from London. There were more
German planes over the coast of Britain
today than at any time since the war
began. Anti-aircraft guns were in action
along the southeast coast today.
Fought in the air. The Battle of Britain
would start on July 10th and would
finish on October 31st, 1940.
>> I was speaking to Captain Eric Brown who
interrogated Guring that Guring at
Nuremberg told him that the Battle of
Britain was a draw.
>> I said to him, "What are your views on
the outcome of the Battle of Britain?"
and he said, "I think it was a draw."
And I said, "How did you arrive at that
conclusion?"
He said, "Well, if you look at the
analysis of the final weeks of the
Battle of Britain, the last week we were
in the ascendancy. In other words, we
had less pilot and aircraft casualties
than the Brits."
Now, if you look at the anal analysis,
this is perfectly true.
>> Although the British had claimed
victory, Hitler's popularity within
Germany was still strong. The Nazi
commanders were all firmly behind
Hitler. However, on May 10th, 1940, one
would take action which would signal
fractures within the regime.
Hitler retained his charismatic [music]
control over the second rank of Nazi
leaders, Guring, Gerbles and so on
during the war. Hess was the only
exception because he was really eased
out of the central decision-making
circles of Nazism and thought he'd try
and get back in a rather muddle-headed
way.
>> One of the great mysteries of World War
II. There is some speculation as to
whether Hitler in fact authorized it
because if we take Hitler as actually
wanting um a negotiated peace with
Britain, not a conquest, it it would
actually make sense. In the most bizarre
and astounding event of the war so far,
Rudolph Hess, number three Nazi, seen
here going about his activities as
confidant and chief party leader for the
Nazi warlord Hitler, is now a prisoner
in Scotland after a mysterious solo
flight from Germany.
>> Had simply got into [music] his head.
But to restore his um status with
Hitler, he would fly to Britain and
negotiate a peace. It was very easy for
the Nazi media to project Hess as
deluded. Indeed, what he did was
remarkable. Firstly, he learned to fly
uh specifically for this purpose.
>> The Nazi leader took off from Augsburg
and headed straight for Western Scotland
where an old friend of his, the Duke of
Hamilton, has an estate. His mission,
who knows?
>> He flew and crash landed on the estate
of the Duke of Hamilton in Scotland. The
choice of landing was significant
because Hamilton had actually been very
sympathetic to Germany [music] before
the war and some suggested a kind of
cryptofascist to himself. But by this
stage he's very anxious to clean up his
act. So he delivers her straight uh to
the authorities.
>> Hitler was furious because of course he
didn't know about it. furious
particularly because it was just before
the invasion of the Soviet Union.
>> As Gerbles and the Nazi propaganda
machine were covering themselves from
the Hest debacle, Hitler was
implementing the start of another
battle. Led by arrogance and
self-belief, he would soon embark on the
largest invasion in the history of
warfare. The attack would stretch along
a 3,000 km front and would send 4
million soldiers into Soviet territory.
It would mark the beginning of the
pivotal phase in deciding the victory of
the war, which would see Nazi popularity
plummet in Germany. It would bring death
and destruction to millions of people.
1940 had seen the height of Hitler and
the Nazi regime's popularity within
Germany. The Battle of Britain [music]
had been unsuccessful, but support was
still strong despite Hess's flight to
Scotland. What would come next, however,
would be a battle led by prejudice and
vanity on the part of Hitler. His own
self-belief convinced him to march on
Moscow and conquer Russia, the very
campaign that Charles I 12th and
Napoleon had failed to achieve.
In a sudden coup, Germany's military
might [music] has been thrown against
her former ally, Russia, in a gigantic
attack by land as well as by air along a
2,000mi front from the Arctic to the
Black Sea.
At first, he was lucky. His
self-confidence paid off. Took the right
land and walked into Austria. All that
built up his self-confidence, not only
with the people, but with himself.
This was the dangerous thing.
>> There are two reasons why Hitler
attacked Soviet Union. First of all, it
was a way of bringing Britain to terms
because he thought already in 1940
that he wasn't going to conquer Britain
by force. Uh he was going to have to
leave Britain totally isolated without
any allies at all. And if he conquered
the Soviet Union, the British surely
would see sense. that have the entire
continent against them.
>> Secondly, his derision of the Bolsheviks
uh them being inherently incompetent and
his [music] racial dismissal of the
Russians. So he believed it would
collapse like a house of cards. The
Bolevik state was rotten to the core.
You had only to kick the door in and the
whole edifice would come crumbling down.
That's what they thought. And [music] I
think flushed with success from the
Blitzkrie in Western Europe, they
thought all they had to do was attack.
In a way, it was a bit silly actually
because that had been the mentality of
1914.
>> With a bit of luck, if he had gone
earlier, he may have succeeded in
temporarily conquering Russia. Today,
American news agencies report Russia is
strongly counterattacking and that less
than 1/50th of Russia's vast area has
been invaded. These pictures show them
the beginning of the blitz that turned
into a siege.
>> There was some encouragement in that
[music] Stalin had done a great deal of
damage to his armed forces through the
purges of the mid later 1930s. But how
Hitler would ever police it for the rest
of the [music] time, I don't think he'd
even begun to think it through.
Panzer troops in action from the Baltic
to the Black Sea. Great clashes between
Russian and German tank squadrons have
been reported.
>> In the autumn of [music] 1941,
the Germans were on course just cutting
through butter. Going to take Moscow,
going to take Lennengrad.
And they didn't. and they were stopped.
>> Operation Barbarasa would be a
definitive turning point in the fortunes
of the Nazi regime. The march on Moscow
was the end of what had started as a
successful campaign. Hitler had gained
many territories in Eastern Europe. But
it was the harsh Soviet winter and the
tough belligerance of the Red Army that
would finally see the Nazis defeated and
home support of the regime finally
turned.
>> Here, apparently the Germans got their
first sight of the Russian scorched
earth tactics. Scorched Earth tactics
that American reporters say should be
even more effective now that winter has
set in. and Hitler's photogenic army
must face General Snow and General Mud.
>> Once you get into 1942, [music]
they're now fighting on quite a number
of fronts.
Army leave is being cancelled, [music]
so people aren't getting home. Food
rationing is getting more stringent.
[music]
People are becoming depressed
and disillusioned.
It was not just the German population
who were becoming despondent. Many
officers in the German army were also
starting to question their furious
actions. Throughout the wars, there were
attempts to assassinate Hitler. Many of
them orchestrated by anti-Hitler
generals [music] and soldiers. Uh but
they could none of them manage it. All
the former social democrats and [music]
communists, I say a third of the
electorate in the last free election in
1932,
they had effectively been brought in
line. Their resistance movements [music]
mostly distributing leaflets and kind of
keep the flame going as it were. They'd
all been suppressed by the Gustapa.
>> It was very difficult to resist in the
Third Reich uh because denunciation was
widespread. if somebody overheard you or
got a clue that you know you were doing
X [music] Y and Zed then they would go
down to Gustapa headquarters and and
turn you in.
>> So the only people who could really
resist as a group were the senior army
officers with a few conservative
politicians attached and they're the
ones who then prepared the assassination
of Hitler as things were beginning to go
really seriously wrong [music] in 1943
to to 4. Klaus von Stalenberg was a
general in the German army who had been
injured serving in North Africa losing
his right hand, two fingers on the left
and also his left eye.
Von Staffenberg was the most unlikely
assassin. He'd been seriously [music]
injured. He could prime the bombing with
great difficulty and so on, but nobody
else could be found to do it. And he was
determined now that his German
patriotism could only be expressed by
destroying Hitler. Hitler would destroy
Germany. If you were a patriot, your job
was to destroy Hitler.
Although the bomb von Stalenberg
detonated, killed four people. Hitler
was shielded by a solid oak table and
was only left with minor injuries. Von
Stafenberg was found guilty of high
treason and subsequently executed.
Having survived the assassination
attempt, Adolf Hitler was still
convinced that the war was for winning.
Even though the German nation suspected
the worst, he's always hoping when he
looks back at history that something
will happen, something will happen
politically. Uh the alliance will fall
apart or Germany will invent an amazing
[music] new weapon, but somehow other
you can pluck uh victory from the jaws
of defeat just as his great hero Fri the
Great had done. I'm not sure there's
ever a point actually at which Hitler
says, "I recognize it. I failed. We're
going to be defeated."
The battle on the Eastern Front turned
into a long war of attrition. The German
army was illprepared for this and the
Russian army with the far greater
resource would in 1944 finally defeat
the attacking German army.
The paradox of the attack eastwards
[music] was that the more territory
Hitler gained, greater was the Jewish
population he acquired.
The war changed everything and Germany's
victories across Europe and then in the
east after June 1941
from having a population of 600,000 Jews
in 1933 the number of Jewish people
under the Reichkes in inverted commas
administrative military control soared
to many millions of people. Hitler's
problem, self-inflicted problem, [music]
is he attacks Poland and the largest
concentration of European Jews falls
into his [music] hands and as he moves
elsewhere in Eastern Europe, more Jews
come under his rule. The original idea
had been to expel German Jews from
[music] Germany and Jews were expelled
into into Poland, for example.
But that doesn't solve the problem once
you've invaded Poland.
The Madagascar plan was an idea to
establish a Jewish colony on the African
island of Madagascar.
It was subsequently shelved in 1942.
>> I don't think anybody ever asked
Madagascar to settle a Jewish colony
there to ship out European Jews, but
that was I think was never really going
to come to anything. There had been talk
about enforced
deportations of a captive Jewish
population out of Germany, out of
Europe. How were they going to do that?
That by its very nature would have been
a brutal, murderous [music] exercise.
The Vanay conference was a meeting of
Nazi officials in Vanc, a suburb of
Berlin to establish a [music] final
solution to the Jewish problem.
They formalized the operation of the
Holocaust while it was already underway,
while it had already started. People
like Aishman Hydrich showed up to take
the decisions in a chillingly
managerial way. No need for Hitler to be
present. They didn't need him. They knew
Hitler would sanction what they were
going to do.
The extermination camps would eventually
operate around the clock. In the last
acts of this brutal conflict, Adolf
Hitler would unleash one final command
that would [music] order the futile
resistance of his party faithful.
War on the Eastern Front was a battle
too far. It signaled the end for the
Nazi regime. The German nation was
heavily rationed and those dwelling in
the urban centers were facing
everinccreasing bombing raids by the
Allied [music] forces. Hitler, however,
remained defiant.
Later on, Hitler lived in a fantasy
world of his own. Even in the last days
of the war, he was conjuring up in his
own mind imaginary armies, secret
weapons,
extraordinary makebelieve scenarios.
>> He maintained his faith
because it was a [music] matter of will.
The 1934 party rally was called triumph
of the will and Hitler and Gerbles to a
very great extent and some other close
followers maintained this belief that
their will would prevail.
>> Nobody had the nerve to [music] try to
disabuse Hitler of his fantasies even in
the last days. In the autumn of 1944,
a group of generals come to Hitler's
headquarters. The generals go in and say
to Hitler, "We are convinced that the
war is lost." [music] They're in there
for about, I don't know, an hour and a
half or something. And they come out
again. Their eyes shining, saying, "The
Furer has convinced us that we can
[music] win the war."
>> By then, he'd already decided that the
German people had betrayed him. They had
proved unworthy of their great destiny
[music] and deserved the fate that was
descending upon them extraordinary
mental and moral universe to inhabit.
June 6th, 1944 saw the D-Day landings
and would be the start of the Allied
invasion of occupied Western Europe.
Germany found they were retreating from
all fronts as the Red Army marched from
the east. Close to defeat, Hitler issued
what became known as the Nero decree. On
March 19th, 1945, [music]
an order was sent out that all German
infrastructures must be destroyed to
prevent the Allies utilizing them as
they advanced. It also called for every
last house and street to be fought for.
>> It happened in small villages
which had had nothing to do with the
war. they had to stand and fight when
when American tanks came. That kind of
thing. It just was absolutely criminal.
>> So he blamed reverses and defeats on the
lack of willpower in his generals, not
on the lack of [music] material or the
superiority of the enemy. It had
terrible repercussions
for Germans
because it meant that the whole of
Germany had to be invaded, fought over,
occupied by foreign troops in a way that
had not happened in the First World War
because Hitler wouldn't surrender.
>> In the closing stages of the war, a
large number of the Nazi faithful
realized that the war was effectively
lost. This resulted in mass suicides
throughout Germany.
There's this feeling of goddamarong, the
twilight of the gods. [music] We all die
together because life after the Reich
isn't worth living. Now, that's an
extraordinary
uh sensation. Uh and I think one can't
fully explain it. You you have to
understand the extraordinarily rigid
hold the regime had on people.
A great many of the [music] party
faithful committed suicide because they
simply couldn't face the idea of German
defeat. They've been fed [music]
propaganda for years that defeat would
mean the partition of Germany. It might
mean the deliberate impoverishment. Um
there were rumors that all German males
would be castrated and all kinds of
extraordinary things went around in
1945. Historians have tried to quantify
the numbers, but in the ghastly chaos of
the Third Reich in its final days, mass
murder, nicolistic orgies of killing by
the the Nazi state in its death throws,
it's hard to know what the the actual
figures really were.
Knowing that the Soviets were advancing
swiftly towards [music] his bunker,
Hitler gave his last will and testament,
making Joseph Gerbles as Reich
Chancellor and naming no one as his
successor as Furer. The next day, April
30th, 1945,
Hitler shot himself. Two of Hitler's
immediate circle, Joseph Gerbles and
Martin Borman, remained loyal to him
right to the end. They stayed [music] in
the bunker in Berlin. uh for Gerbles
there was nowhere else to go. He felt
that if if if the third right collapsed,
if Hitler was killed, that was it. That
was everything was over.
>> An extraordinary
sense of apocalypse seemed to overtake
them and they felt that that was the
only course of action open to them.
On May 1st, Joseph Gerbles and his wife
Magda committed suicide, [music]
but before doing so killed their six
children by drugging them and then
poisoning them with cyanide.
Both Himler and Gerring would commit
suicide as well. But this was not before
they were interrogated by the Allies.
Captain Eric Brown, posted to Germany to
look for jet wind tunnels, was tasked
with the job of identifying Himmler and
was able to interrogate Guring.
Himmler was arrested near the Danish
border with false papers.
The warrant officer phoned headquarters
at Lunberg
and said, "We've picked up somebody who
we think might be Hitler. Could you come
up and identify him? You said when you
saw him learn in civil life that he used
to walk with a slightly peculiar gate
and uh could you come up and try and
identify [music] this guy?
So I went up the B step. As soon as I
walked in I knew it was him. I mean even
without making him walk.
Absolute coward.
I think he was frightened out of his
life. Uh,
always
trying to evade anything that directly
threatened him.
>> Accompanied by these two SS men, Hinrich
Himmler, most hated man in Europe, was
captured by British troops outside this
town. Concealed in Himler's mouth was a
tiny vial of deadly poison. While deemed
salmon, he swallowed it.
Guring was in American custody and Eric
was able to ask him key questions about
Nazi aircraft strategy.
He was charismatic, very intelligent. He
came out of World War I with great
honor, had a a huge reputation [music]
in Germany, a good man who went very
wrong. He was corrupted by the system he
joined and he lost all his qualities of
honor and began to really
lust for power and luxury
and uh that of course was his total
downfall.
At Lunabach, Germany before a British
military court, the greatest mass murder
trial in history. These Nazis were
guards at notorious Belson concentration
camp where 4 million prisoners died. The
end of the war signaled the beginning of
peace for many across Europe and the
rest of the world. There was a tangible
sense of relief in the air. [music] But
as occupied land was liberated, the full
horror of the Nazi regime was revealed.
Eric Brown was part of the liberation of
Berg and Bellson.
>> Piles of dead bodies, piles of walking
dead. Really, just a horror story.
>> Now, Bailson, the human slaughterhouse
where numberless victims were once
burned to death, is itself put to the
torch.
Nearby, Nazi women guards are lined up
for questioning.
He wanted me to interrogate a camp
common dad who was called Ysef Karma
and the lady camp commoner. [music]
>> Kramer's chief saddest was Irma Graca in
curls whose name struck terror into the
hearts of Belson's inmates.
>> She's the worst human being I've ever
met. Cruelty was her trade. There was
nothing too cruel for this woman to do.
When it came to interrogating her, I
asked her if she had her time over
again, would she do all this? She
refused to answer. After about four or
five times like this, she suddenly leapt
to her feet and gave the Nazi salute,
shouted, "Hitler, sat down, and refused
to talk."
But um
we executed the lot. You can hardly
defend yourself when outside the window
there's a pile of bodies as high as the
[music] ceiling in a pit. News real
films of the atrocities at Bellson
shocked the world. Even death for Kramer
and his gang cannot avenge the crimes of
the beasts of Bellson.
What started as Hitler's strong
anti-semitic beliefs in the wake [music]
of World War I ended as what we now know
as the Holocaust. 6 million Jews were
murdered along with tens of thousands of
gypsies, homosexuals, communists,
mentally ill, and the physically
disabled.
In the aftermath of the war, the Allied
forces would soon stake their own
territorial claims, which would leave
the conquered nation divided.
>> Germany in 1945 was an extraordinary
mess. 60% of its urban area had been
obliterated from the air.
>> Germany was occupied by the Allied
powers, the Soviet Union, [music] the
French, British, and Americans. Very
heavy military occupation.
It was economically impoverished. It was
difficult to see in fact in 1945 where
Germany was going to go, how Germans
were going to survive. Widespread
hunger, even starvation in places.
>> There were all kinds of measures to stop
any recrudesence of Nazism. Nazi laws
are revoked. There's a re-education
effort of trying to educate Germans in
the evils [music] of Nazism. But in a
sense, that's all less important than
the fact that Nazism had brought in the
end nothing but death and destruction.
After the war, the nation of Germany
would be split in two. To the east, the
Soviet occupied area became the German
Democratic Republic. The area to the
west, which Britain, France, and the US
occupied, became the Federal Republic of
Germany. This division was most [music]
notably illustrated in Berlin.
The Berlin Wall was erected in 1961 and
would be a chilling visual reminder of a
nation divided.
I was sent back to Germany in mid
[music] 1950s.
I found it difficult to reform
relationship with some of them whom I
knew what they had done in the war. But
in general, I realized that some of them
had been led like sheep to the
slaughter.
>> I think post-war Germany is a great epic
[music] in the act of remembrance and
admission. For a nation to confront its
guilt like that is [music] extraordinary
because a lot of other nations have a
lot of other skeletons in the cupboard.
Hitler remains a source of intrigue for
many people throughout the world.
Hitler exerts a kind of fascination that
you could never really imagine. [music]
We spend so much time writing books
about programs about Hitler and so on. I
think Hitler would have been amazed
[music] by the extent of historical
attention that's paid to him.
You'll always get young bloods who will
be attracted to the style of the Nazi
regime.
>> They've actually given us the image not
of themselves but of their ideal.
It is an extraordinary story how this
nondescript [music]
man, stateless radical politician with a
whole lot of wacky ideas in the 1920s
could suddenly become Germanist
dictator, then unleash the [music]
largest war and embark on the biggest
crime the world has ever known. And I I
I think that the public 70 years on is
still fascinated by those paradoxes.
[music]
>> Today, Germany is a nation united. The
economic miracle that West Germany
experienced in the 1950s, supported by
the Marshall Plan gave them the basis to
develop a strong economy and political
stability. The real miracle, however,
should be credited to the people of
Germany. By confronting their own brutal
history, they have allowed the world to
learn from the mistakes made in their
past.
Although persecution, hatred, and war
are still a global problem, Germany has
sanctioned its history to be used as the
marker of a cruelty which should never
again be repeated.
[cheering]